Guide to the Jazz Loft Project Records, 1950-2012 and undated RL.10001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jazz Loft Project records
1950-2012 and undated, bulk 2002-2009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Stephenson, Sam
RL.10001
20 Linear Feet
The Jazz Loft Project Records consist of the research and administrative records of author Sam Stephenson's Jazz Loft Project, which documented the events and inhabitants -- including W. Eugene Smith, Hall Overton, and David X. Young -- of 821 6th Avenue, New York City, in the late 1950s and early 1960s. The records include the tapes of an extensive oral history project conducted by Stephenson from 1998 to 2010, general research and administrative notes, logs describing the content of the audio recordings W. Eugene Smith made at the loft, and original audio recordings of Hall Overton's compositions.
Collection Overview
The Jazz Loft Project Records include administrative documents, audio and video recordings, and collected research associated with key participants and events in the history of the Jazz Loft building, located at 821 Sixth Avenue in New York City. The collection includes significant documentation of the jazz music scene in New York from 1955-1971, and the life and work of photographer W. Eugene Smith, composer Hall F. Overton, and jazz musician Thelonious Monk. Also of note are materials that document the collection of oral histories, the design and implementation of exhibitions, and conservation reports on audio recordings all related to the Jazz Loft Project. Items in the collection range from 1950 to 2012, with the bulk being created between 2002 and 2009.
A majority of materials in this collection consist of the project's financial and logistical documentation, oral history interviews in print, audio, and video formats, audio reel analysis notes, and biographical/historical articles. Examples of these types of documentation include correspondence, book drafts, promotional materials for exhibitions and events, research notes, and interview transcripts.
The collection contains 824 audiovisual items, including microcassettes, audiocassettes, VHS videocassettes, ¼-inch audio reels, DVDs, CDs, mini-DV videocassettes, and digital audio tapes (DAT). The bulk of this media is associated with oral history interviews, events and exhibitions, and research related to the Jazz Loft Project, but there are also items tangentially related to the Project, such as commercial music recordings, recordings of concerts and performances, original recordings of Hall Overton's opera Huck Finn, and published documentary footage related to W. Eugene Smith and other artists.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials may require production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Biographical/Historical note
From 1954 to 1972, the building at 821 6th Avenue, New York, NY functioned as practice space, crash pad, art studio, and social hub for a variety of musicians and artists including noted photographer W. Eugene Smith, painter (and Loft founder) David X. Young, composer/musician Hall Overton, and jazz legend Thelonious Monk. Wiring the "Jazz Loft" with microphones and recorders, and taking tens of thousands of photographs during his tenure in the Loft (1957-1971), Smith created a sprawling aural and visual portrait of jazz as it was lived by its creators, and of life in Manhattan's Flower District during the middle of the twentieth century. Of note, Smith's microphones captured interactions between Hall Overton and Thelonious Monk, during their collaboration on the compositions Monk's large band would perform for the groundbreaking Town Hall Concert in 1959. Smith recorded and collected thousands of hours worth of material that went unheard for many years.
Author Sam Stephenson found the tapes in the W. Eugene Smith collection at the University of Arizona's Center for Creative Photography, while researching his book Dream Street: W. Eugene Smith's Pittsburgh Project. Stephenson subsequently organized the Jazz Loft Project through the Center for Documentary Studies at Duke University. The goal of the Project was to digitize the Smith recordings, analyze their content, and develop a more comprehensive historical portrait of the Jazz Loft through the collection of oral histories from people affiliated with the building. Leveraging successful grant funding with partnerships with the Center for Creative Photography and WNYC, the Jazz Loft Project became a book, an exhibition, and an informing text for performances of Monk's work and dramatic interpretations of the Loft scene. The oral histories document and discuss a wide range of topics and people, but focus primarily on the lives and work of W. Eugene Smith, Hall Overton, and Thelonious Monk, along with cultural/musical events that took place at the Jazz Loft.
Sources
http://www.jazzloftproject.org The Jazz Loft Project Records, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Related Materials
David X. Young Films, 1955-2007, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Oral histories (document genre); Jazz -- Illinois -- Chicago; Jazz; Women jazz musicians; Digital audio tapes; Photography -- United States -- 20th century; Jazz -- New York (State) -- New York -- History; Jazz -- New York (State) -- New York.; Mini-DV; DVDs; Architecture -- New York (State) -- New York -- 20th century; Overton, Hall; Monk, Thelonious; Young, David X., 1930-2001; Smith, W. Eugene, 1918-1978.
- Oral Histories, 1991-2010; 614 items
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains oral history transcripts in printed and electronic form, along with audio and video recordings of oral history interviews completed as part of the Jazz Loft Project. Many interviewees either visited or lived in the Jazz Loft building--e.g. David X. Young, Nancy Overton, Ron Free, Carole Thomas, and James Stephenson. Other interviewees were family members, musicians or artists in the New York city cultural scene, or scholars with pertinent information and stories that related to the Jazz Loft building--e.g. Whitney Balliett (jazz critic for the New Yorker), Robin D. G. Kelley (Thelonious Monk biographer), and the children of W. Eugene Smith. The original oral history recordings are closed to use, but digital access copies are available.
  - Albert, Calvin, 2003 August 20; Archival Resource Key; 1
    Calvin Albert (1918-2007) was born in Grand Rapids, Michigan. He was a sculptor and friend of Jazz Loft resident Hall Overton, and he occasionally played drums in the loft.
    In this oral history, Albert talks about his upbringing in Grand Rapids, MI, his art education at the New Bauhaus Institute in Chicago, and his time as a musician and teacher in New York City. Trained as a sculptor and illustrator, Albert taught at Pratt Institute in Brooklyn, but also found time to play drums in many jam sessions and rehearsals at the Jazz Loft. Other topics of discussion in this interview include Hall Overton's life and relationships, Albert's health problems since childhood, and the mid-20th century art world in New York City.
    - Calvin Albert Transcript, 2002-2008 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Calvin Albert I, 8/20/03, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, 2003 August 20 (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0001)
    - Calvin Albert II, 8/20/03, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, 2003 August 20 (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0002)
    - Calvin Albert III, 8/21/03, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, 2003 August 20 (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0003)
    - Calvin Albert, 8/20/03, I, Compact disc, Transcription copy, 2003 August 20 (Box 29, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0001)
    - Calvin Albert, II, 8/20/03, Compact disc, Transcription copy, 2003 August 20 (Box 29, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0002)
    - Calvin Albert, III, 8/21/03, Compact disc, Transcription copy, 2003 August 20 (Box 29, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0003)
    - Calvin Albert, I/3, 8/20/03, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2003 August 20 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0001)
    - Calvin Albert, I, 8/20/03, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2003 August 20 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0002)
    - Calvin Albert, II of 3, 8/20/03, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2003 August 20 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0003)
    - Calvin Albert, II, 8/20/03, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2003 August 20 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0004)
    - Calvin Albert, III, 8/21/03, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2003 August 20 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0005)
    - Calvin Albert, 3/3, 8/20/03, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2003 August 20 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0006)
    - Calvin Albert, III, 8-20-03, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2003 August 20 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0007)
  - Allemana, Mike, undated; Archival Resource Key; 2
    Mike Allemana (b. 1969) was born in Elmhurst, IL. As a jazz guitarist in Chicago, he played with Von Freeman and Lin Halliday in the 1990's.
    In this oral history, while briefly describing their own lives and musical backgrounds, Mike Allemana and Dennis Carroll talk primarily about the life, reputation, and death of saxophonist and frequent Jazz Loft visitor, Lin Halliday. Halliday's drug use, family history, and experiences playing in New York, Nashville, Little Rock, and Chicago are also discussed.
    - Mike Allemana & Dennis Carroll Transcript, 2002-2008 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Mike Allemana - Chicago, Dennis Carroll, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, undated; 61 minutes (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0004)
    - Mike Allemana, Dennis Carroll, Mini-dv videocassette, Recorder original, undated (Box 22, Video-cassette RL10001-MDV-0001)
    - Mike Allemana & Dennis Carroll, -Chicago-, Dan Sam, Dennis - out first, Mike [?], Dennis returns ~ 17:30, cont'd, ends ~ 38:00, restarts w/out listen for several minutes to get all Audio., ~to end of tape, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, undated (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0008)
  - Amoss, Frank, 2003 June 19; Archival Resource Key; 3
    Frank Amoss (b. 1936) was born in Baltimore, MD. He was a drummer and lived on the fifth floor of the Jazz Loft building from June-November, 1961.
    In this oral history, Amoss discusses his musical beginnings as a player in the Army and with the Dean Hudson band. Upon his relocation to New York City in 1961, Amoss immediately became involved with the city's jazz community, moving into the Jazz Loft only a couple of weeks after arriving in the city. Amoss also talks about the interaction between musicians and the musicians' union, as well as other musicians who frequented the Jazz Loft including Ronnie Free, Pete Yellin,and Dudley Watkins.
    - Frank Amoss Transcript, 2002-2008 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Frank Amoss, 6/19/03, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, 2003 June 19; 63 minutes (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0005)
    - Frank Amoss, 6/19/03, Mini-dv videocassette, Recorder original, 2003 June 19 (Box 22, Video-cassette RL10001-MDV-0002)
    - Frank Amos, 1/1, 1/1, Compact disc, Transcription copy, 2003 June 19 (Box 29, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0004)
    - Frank Amos, 6-19-03, [+ notes on back of cassette case], Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2003 June 19 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0009)
  - Arnold, Roberta, 2000 October 29; Archival Resource Key; 4
    Roberta Arnold (b. ca. 1941) frequented the Jazz Loft with saxophonist Ronnie Cuber in 1961-62 (they later married and then divorced). At the time, she was a dancer, and she later became an artist manager.
    In this oral history, Arnold talks about her first visit to the Jazz Loft with Joe Lopes in 1961. She discusses the generally poor treatment of women musicians and singers within the jazz community, as well as the competitive, experimental atmosphere at the Jazz Loft. Arnold also mentions the physical state of the Jazz Loft building, W. Eugene Smith's studio, and other musicians she encountered at the Loft including Jimmy Stevenson, Chick Corea, and Ronnie Cuber.
    - Roberta Arnold Transcript, 2002-2008 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Eddie Bert 10-28-00, Roberta Arnold 10-29-00, Manny Duran 10-29-00, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, 2000 October 29; 19 minutes (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0006)
    - Eddie Bert, 10-28-00; Roberta Arnold, 10-29-00, Compact disc, Transcription copy, 2000 October 29 (Box 29, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0008)
    - Roberta Arnold cont'd, 10-29-00, Manny Duran, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2000 October 29 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0010)
    - Eddie Bert, 10-28-00, Roberta Arnold, 10-29-00, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2000 October 29 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0013)
  - Avakian, George, 2006 January 11; Archival Resource Key; 5
    George Avakian (b. 1919) is a Russian-born American record producer and executive. He has produced albums by Miles Davis and other Jazz Musicians, and he is known for his work with Columbia records.
    - George Avakian I, 1/11/06, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, 2006 January 11 (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0007)
    - George Avakian II, 1/11/06, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, 2006 January 11 (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0008)
    - George Avakian, 1/11/06, I, Compact disc, Transcription copy, 2006 January 11 (Box 29, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0005)
    - George Avakian, 1/11/06, II, Compact disc, Transcription copy, 2006 January 11 (Box 29, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0006)
  - Balliett, Whitney, 2002 January 16; Archival Resource Key; 6
    Whitney Balliett (1926-2007) was a jazz critic and book reviewer for the New Yorker from 1954-2001.
    In this oral history, Balliett talks about his experiences as a jazz critic and enthusiast, the development and documentation of the New York City jazz scene starting in the late 1950's, and the development of the jazz sound over the years. Balliett also discusses his role as consultant for the CBS "Sound of Jazz" program and how his personal writing influences, including Joseph Mitchell, affected the style of his jazz column for the New Yorker.
    - Whitney Balliett Transcript, 2002-2008 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Whitney Balliett, 1/16/02, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, 2002 January 16; 117 minutes (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0009)
    - Whitney Balliett, 1/16/02, Compact disc, Transcription copy, 2002 January 16 (Box 29, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0007)
    - Whitney Balliett, 1-16-02, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2002 January 16 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0011)
    - Whitney Balliett, 1-16-02, cont'd, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2002 January 16 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0012)
  - Bateman, Edgar, undated; 23
    In this oral history, drummer Edgar Bateman discusses his early life as a musician. Also discussed is the strong role of music in his family, his education as a musician, and various jobs he held.
    - Edgar Bateman Jr. w/Sam Stephenson Edgar Bateman III /Private not for public or scholars, Compact disc, undated (Box 31, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0072, Box 24, Video-cassette RL10001-MDV-0142)
    - Edgar Bateman Jr. w/Sam Stephenson Edgar Bateman III /Private not for public or scholars, Mini-dv videocassette, Recorder original, 2009 November 5 (Box 24, Video-cassette RL10001-MDV-0142)
  - Bert, Eddie, 2000 October 28; Archival Resource Key; 8
    Eddie Bert (1922-2012) was born in Yonkers, New York. He was a jazz trombonist and participated in rehearsals in the Loft with Thelonious Monk in 1955 for an event at the 92nd Street Y, and as a member of Monk's 1959 Town Hall big band, and his 1963 and 1964 big bands.
    In multiple interviews, Bert talks about his upbringing in Yonkers, NY and his musical development as a trombonist, but focuses primarily on his direct involvement with Thelonious Monk as part of the band who performed at Town Hall in 1959. Bert discusses his personal photography, band rehearsals at the Jazz Loft, Hall Overton's relationship with Monk, and Overton's role in the music's arrangement. Also mentioned are Bert's experiences working with Benny Goodman and Charles Mingus, his early musical work in the Army, and Bert's views on the ways technology has impacted the development of jazz.
    - Eddie Bert Transcripts, 2002-2008 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Eddie Bert 10-28-00, Roberta Arnold 10-29-00, Manny Duran 10-29-00, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, 2000 October 28 (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0006)
    - Eddie Beit, 10-28-00; Roberta Arnold, 10-29-00, Compact disc, Transcription copy, 2000 October 28 (Box 29, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0008)
    - Eddie Bert, 10-28-00, Roberta Arnold, 10-29-00, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2000 October 28 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0013)
    - Eddie Bert, 5-10-05, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, 2005 May 10 (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0011)
    - Eddie Bert, 1/2, 5-10-05, no DAT, Mini-dv videocassette, Recorder original, 2005 May 10 (Box 22, Video-cassette RL10001-MDV-0003)
    - Eddie Bert #2, 5-10-05, interview, with DAT, Mini-dv videocassette, Recorder original, 2005 May 10 (Box 22, Video-cassette RL10001-MDV-0004)
    - Eddie Bert, 6-10-05, Compact disc, Transcription copy, 2005 May 10 (Box 29, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0009)
    - Eddie Bert, 5-10-05, Sam S., Dan P., Danbury, CT, wife possibly on tape?, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2005 May 10 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0014)
  - Bley, Paul, 2004 September 27; Archival Resource Key; 9
    Paul Bley (b. 1932) was born in Montreal. A pianist and free jazz musician, Bley participated in Jazz Loft jam sessions between 1955 and 1964.
    In this oral history, Bley talks about his experiences playing in jam sessions at the Jazz Loft and his connection with Hall Overton, whom he saw as a musical mentor. Also discussed are Bley's views about the effects of drug abuse on musicians, how jam sessions changed free jazz, W. Eugene Smith's presence at the Jazz Loft, and other players on the scene including Roland Kirk, Henry Grimes, and Pepper Adams.
    - Paul Bley Transcript, 2002-2008 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Paul Bley CD 2 9/27/04, Compact disc, 2004 September 27 (Box 35, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0230)
    - Paul Bley CD 3 9/27/04, Compact disc, 2004 September 27 (Box 35, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0231)
    - Paul Bley CD 1 9/27/04, Compact disc, 2004 September 27 (Box 30, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0265)
    - Paul Bley I, 9-30-04, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, 2004 September 30 (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0012)
    - Paul Bley II, 9-30-04, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, 2004 September 30 (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0013)
    - Paul Bley 3, 9-30-04, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, 2004 September 30 (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0014)
    - Paul Bley, 9-30-04, tape 1/3, Mini-dv videocassette, Recorder original, 2004 September 30 (Box 22, Video-cassette RL10001-MDV-0005)
    - Paul Bley, 9-30-04, tape 2/3, Mini-dv videocassette, Recorder original, 2004 September 30 (Box 22, Video-cassette RL10001-MDV-0006)
    - Paul Bley, 9-30-04, tape 3/3, Mini-dv videocassette, Recorder original, 2004 September 30 (Box 22, Video-cassette RL10001-MDV-0007)
    - Paul Bley, I, 9-30-04, Compact disc, Transcription copy, 2004 September 30 (Box 29, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0010)
    - Paul Bley, II, 9-30-04, Compact disc, Transcription copy, 2004 September 30 (Box 29, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0011)
    - Paul Bley, 3, 9-30-04, Compact disc, Transcription copy, 2004 September 30 (Box 29, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0012)
    - Paul Bley, I, 9-30-04, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2004 September 30 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0015)
    - Paul Bley, II, 9-30-04, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2004 September 30 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0016)
    - Paul Bley, III, 9-30-04, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, 2004 September 30 (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0017)
  - Bouille, John, undated; Archival Resource Key; 10
    John Bouille is a jazz radio personality who lives in Cary, NC.
    - John Bouille, Charles Tolliver, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, undated (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0015)
  - Brenner, Lauren, 2009 September 08; Archival Resource Key; 11
    Lauren Brenner was a contributer to the Jazz Loft Project from UNC Chapel Hill.
    - Lauren Brenner Jazz Loft CDS, 9-8-09, Sam Stephenson - Int, Dan Partridge - Vid, Mini-dv videocassette, Recorder original, 2009 September 08 (Box 22, Video-cassette RL10001-MDV-0008)
    - 9-08-09; Lauren Brenner interview w/Sam Stephenson audio-from video camera DVMini; Dan Partridge @ CDS, Compact disc, 2009 September 8 (Box 32, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0117)
  - Brookmeyer, Bob, 2007 December 20; Archival Resource Key; 12
    Bob Brookmeyer (1929-2011) was born in Kansas City, MO. He was a pianist, trombonist, arranger, and professor at the New England conservatory. He was a friend of David X. Young and Hall Overton, and he participated in many Jazz Loft jam sessions between 1954 and 1959.
    In this oral history, Brookmeyer discusses his memories of the Jazz Loft and goes into great detail about many of the artists and musicians who populated the scene including Zoot Sims, Salvador Dali, Lee Konitz, David X. Young, Teddy Charles, and Ronnie Free. Brookmeyer talks about the influence of the Jazz Loft on the music scene and how it created a creative space for experimentation and community.
    - Bob Brookmeyer Transcript, 2002-2008 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Bob Brookmeyer, 12/20/07, Compact disc, Transcription copy, 2007 December 20; 41 minutes (Box 29, Audio-cd RL10001-CD-0013)
  - Carroll, Dennis, undated; 13
    Dennis Carroll is a jazz bassist in Chicago.
    - Mike Allemana & Dennis Carroll Transcript, 2002-2008 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Mike Allemana - Chicago, Dennis Carroll, Digital audio tape, Recorder original, undated (Box 19, Audio-cassette RL10001-DAT-0004)
    - Mike Allemana, Dennis Carroll, Mini-dv videocassette, Recorder original, undated (Box 22, Video-cassette RL10001-MDV-0001)
    - Mike Allemana & Dennis Carroll, -Chicago-, Dan Sam, Dennis - out first, Mike [?], Dennis returns ~ 17:30, cont'd, ends ~ 38:00, restarts w/out listen for several minutes to get all Audio., ~to end of tape, Standard Audio-cassette, Transcription copy, undated (Box 25, Audio-cassette RL10001-CS-0008)
  - Charles, Teddy, 2002 June 27; Archival Resource Key; 14
    Teddy Charles (1928-2012) was born Theodore Charles Cohen in Chicopee Falls, MA. He was a jazz vibraphonist, pianist, and arranger. A close friend of Hall Overton. Charles participated in many jam sessions during the Jazz Loft era.